Wealthy Barber is a classic Canadian
personal finance book first published in
1989 that has sold over 2 million copies
in Canada. The author Dave Chilton has
come out with a fully updated 2025
edition of the book full of top-notch
personal finance advice on investing,
spending, estate planning, and
insurance. I have read the book twice
now, and in this video I'm going to go
through the points that I think everyone
needs to know. I'm not affiliated with
Dave or his company. I may be a little
biased because this channel is mentioned
in the book and my testimonial is on the
back cover. I know that was a bit of a
humble brag, but come on, it's it's
pretty cool. I meant what I wrote there
on the back of the book. This is the
best and most approachable introduction
to personal finance that I have ever
read. I think this book is a great read
for anyone and an excellent gift for
someone you want to share good financial
planning principles with. Or, you know,
you could just send them this video. No,
but also buy the book. Sorry, Dave. I'm
Ben Felix, chief investment officer at
PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell you
why The Wealthy Barber is a book worth
reading.
The Wealthy Barber is written as a story
with character development, unique
personalities, and lots of dry humor. It
starts with a Canadian couple, Matt and
Maddie, who decide they want to learn
about personal finance. They ask Matt's
parents for help and they get referred
by them to their local barber, Roy, who
we find out is himself financially
successful despite not having an
abnormally high income or having
received a big inheritance. He is the
wealthy barber. Roy is also an excellent
personal finance teacher, having helped
many people over the years, including
Matt's parents. The book follows Matt
and Mattiey's visits with Roy as they
learn about personal finance. They're
joined by Matt's overspending but
successful entrepreneur sister, Jess,
his best friend Kyle Sorav, a newcomer
to Canada who lives in Royy's apartment
building, and some of Royy's regular
customers who hang out in the barber
shop, and they all contribute to the
discussions. This writing style,
conversational with lots of back and
forth on questions that readers likely
have, makes the information approachable
for anyone. All right, as much as I do
like the writing, I'm not just here to
praise the book. I want to give you its
main lessons. Again, I'm sorry, Dave. I
do hope people still read the book. The
first lesson imparted by Roy is you can
do this. There's absolutely nothing
we're going to cover that you're not
capable of fully understanding and
implementing successfully. You can start
managing your own money very well quite
soon. For many people, that is a huge
lesson. Finance and numbers more
generally can be intimidating, but
becoming good at managing your finances
is not a mathematical endeavor. As Roy
says in that first conversation, none of
the important financial planning
concepts are complex. This is such an
important point. Roy is absolutely
correct that smart investing and
financial planning are easy to
understand. They're not always easy to
execute due to human psychology, but
they should be easy to understand. If
you can't understand an investment
product or financial planning strategy,
there's a good chance you should avoid
it altogether. In their next
conversation, Roy introduces his golden
rule. Save and invest at least 10% of
your net income for the future. This
rule is powerful due to the nature of
compounding. Saving and investing
consistently over time eventually
results in the returns from your
investments far exceeding your ability
to save. Compounding is both powerful
and poorly understood. Humans are just
not wired to process exponential growth,
which is exactly what compounding
results in. Roy then explains that to be
truly useful, the first rule needs to be
paired with the second rule. And
according to Roy, the three most
important words in personal finance, pay
yourself first. Roy explains that saving
is hard. Putting money away for your
future self who feels like a bit of a
stranger is competing with spending on
your present self who's dealing with
immediate needs, a rising cost of
living, the addiction-like psychology of
spending money, and our innate desire to
keep up with the people around us. Not
to mention all the businesses doing
everything they can to influence you to
spend your money on their products and
services. Paying yourself first, putting
a portion of your money into long-term
investments or savings for some other
short or medium-term goal before you
have a chance to spend it takes away
that temptation. Roy explains that while
taking 10% or more of your income away
seems difficult to do, once you start,
you realize that a lot of your spending
was on things you didn't really need. As
Roy concludes the lesson, Sorov chimes
in to summarize, save first, spend the
rest good, spend first, save the rest
bad. Now, I do feel compelled to say
that many economists would disagree with
this advice. It could make sense to save
less early on in life and more later
when your income is higher. And
similarly, it could make sense to save
more or less in a given year depending
on your income and spending needs. That
implies spending first and saving the
rest. But as a general rule, to get
people engaged with long-term thinking,
saving, and investing, pay yourself
first at a rate of around 10% of your
net income is a solid foundation. It's
certainly better than not saving at all.
And as you adjust to having a little
less cash in your budget, it builds the
reflex to carefully consider the
difference between spending needs and
wants, which most people probably don't
do enough of. I'll come back to that
later with some useful wisdom from Roy.
The next session with Roy covers
investing. First, Roy prompts the group
to consider why investing is important.
They collectively offer several correct
reasons, including to fight off
inflation, funding your future financial
goals, and harnessing the power of
compounding. Roy offers up a nice
catchphrase to explain what he thinks
successful investing looks like. Be an
owner, not a loner. He's drawing the
distinction here between stocks and
bonds. A stock is a piece of ownership
in a business, while a bond is a loan to
a company or government. In general,
stocks are riskier and have higher
expected returns than bonds. Roy
explains that stocks must have higher
expected returns than bonds because they
are riskier to own. With stocks, you're
participating in the potential upside
and potential downside of the financial
performance of real businesses. Some
businesses do really well while many do
poorly in the long run. Bonds are much
safer because you get roughly the same
return whether the company's financial
performance is good or bad. And if it's
really bad, leading the company to shut
down, bond holders often stand to
recover some value while stockholders do
not. Government bonds are even safer.
Roy explains that in the long run,
stocks are a bet on human ingenuity.
Being an owner, a stockholder, lets you
participate in the ongoing human
innovation that our whole economic
system is based on. It is hard to
disagree with Roy here, and I have done
videos on the merits of 100% equity
portfolios, but it's also true that the
volatility of 100% equity portfolios is
too much for some people to handle.
Asset allocation decisions should be
made based on your ability, willingness,
and need to take on the volatility of
stocks to earn higher expected returns.
The group is listening intently to Roy
here, but they voiced their concern that
they don't know anything about stocks or
the stock market. Kyle, Matt's best
friend, even explains that some of his
friends lost a bunch of money picking
stocks during the COVID boom, like
Pelaton is one example that he gives,
which came crashing back down to earth.
Roy explains that you need no knowledge
to invest successfully in the stock
market. He even goes as far as saying
that for 99% of people, more financial
knowledge makes them worse, not better
at investing. I would qualify this a
little bit. Certain knowledge, like the
idea that most people can't beat the
market and that index funds are sensible
investments for most people, is
extremely useful knowledge. Knowing how
to follow the performance of individual
stocks or the direction of interest
rates is probably not useful, and I
agree with Roy here, likely to do more
harm than good. People often tend to
sabotage their own returns by
overtrading, timing the market, and
investing in stocks that grab their
attention, all of which lead to lower
returns, and those problems are
exacerbated when people who think they
have some knowledge follow the market
closely. Roy goes on to explain that
successful investing requires minimal
investment knowledge because simply
buying all of the stocks or a close
approximation of it is the most
consistently successful investment
strategy in history. It beats the vast
majority of professional investors and
the vast majority of individual stocks.
It's next to impossible to consistently
separate winning and losing stocks
before the fact. But doing so is not
necessary because all of the stocks
together, including both the winners and
the losers, have historically had more
than enough return to propel most people
successfully toward their long-term
goals. This approach works because while
lots of companies are losers in the long
run, the winners tend to win big. The
most you can lose in a stock is 100% of
your investment, but when you own a big
winner, you can gain far more than that.
We can't identify those winners and
losers before the fact, but owning all
of the stocks in the market means that
you will always hold the big winners.
This effect, which is called skewess, is
what makes owning the market so
difficult to beat. This is also part of
the explanation for why professional
money managers consistently fail to
deliver market beating returns. The
other reason is their high fees. Here in
Canada, we still have a huge portion of
our investment assets in high fee funds
that aim to beat the market. While as
expected, very few are actually
successful. Roy admits that he too at
one time had invested in actively
managed mutual funds, but he eventually
saw the light after underperforming
consistently. Between the skewess in
stock returns and the high fees charged
by the managers hoping to beat the
market, trying to beat the market is a
losing game. This again leads to the
simple conclusion requiring little
knowledge to simply buy the market. The
good news is that there are lowcost
investment vehicles called index funds
that do aim to buy all of the stocks in
a broad market index. A broad market
index is a grouping of stocks that has
been assembled to represent an entire
stock market. In Canada, we even have
asset allocation ETFs which give you a
globally diversified portfolio of index
funds. Roy suggests that those asset
allocation ETFs are a good option for
many people and I agree with them. The
group also raises the point that while
being an owner not a loner may have made
sense in the past, the future is
perilous. We have global warming, Russia
and Ukraine, and divisive politics, all
making the outlook for the global
economy look weak at best, making being
an owner, being an investor in the stock
market less compelling now than it may
have been in the past. Roy does
something here that I love. He brings up
history. Roy reads a headline that he
keeps laminated on his counter, and I'm
going to repeat it here. It is a gloomy
moment in history. Not in the lifetime
of any man who reads this paper has
there been such grave and deep
apprehension. The United States is beset
with racial, industrial, and commercial
chaos. Drifting we know not where, and
Russia hangs like a storm cloud on the
horizon. Of our troubles, no man can see
an end. The group assumes this is from a
current paper, but Roy explains that
it's from Harper's magazine in 1847. I I
learned this lesson early on in my
career. When you look around at the
state of the world, it always, always,
always feels like some un unprecedented
disaster is unfolding before our eyes,
making it feel like a particularly bad
time to invest in the market right now.
The reality is that it always feels that
way. Wars, threats of war, discouraging
economic data, natural disasters, and a
ton of uncertainty about the future are
persistent realities. That doesn't go
away. And yes, that makes investing
risky. But the very nature of that risk
is why we expect to earn positive
returns in the long run. If there were
no risk, we would expect to earn the
kind of returns that you get from a
guaranteed investment certificate, which
are much lower. With index funds and
expected returns out of the way, Roy
goes on to explain Canadian account
types, including the RRSP and TFSA. RSPS
and TFSAs are like containers that
investments can be held in. The RRSP is
a pre-tax savings account, meaning that
contributions are made with pre-tax
dollars. This is implemented in practice
with a dollar for-doll tax deduction
when you contribute to your RRSP,
reducing your taxable income by the same
amount. When you eventually withdraw
from your RRSP, the withdrawal is fully
taxable as income. The TFSA is an after
tax savings account, meaning that
contributions are made with dollars you
have already paid income tax on, and
accordingly, there is no tax on
withdrawals. That's all pretty
straightforward, but Roy offers the crew
an illustration comparing the two
account types that I think everyone
needs to understand. Say you have a 30%
tax rate and contributed $5,000 to an
RRSP. 3,500 of those dollars are your
after tax dollars and 1,500 are deferred
income tax dollars. The RRSP allows you
to invest those future tax dollars. It
allows you to defer income tax. Invest
that at 8% for 30 years and you have
just over $50,000. Then withdraw it at
the same 30% tax rate and you have just
over $35,000.
Now let's look at the TFSA. Only after
tax dollars can go into the TFSA.
Following the $5,000 pre-tax RRSP
contribution, the TFSA will get a $3,500
after tax contribution since the TFSA
does not offer tax deferral. Invest that
for 30 years at 8% and you have just
over $35,000, exactly the same as the
after tax outcome for the RRSP. This
shows something important and often
misunderstood. When your income tax rate
is held constant, your after tax dollars
in both the RRSP and TFSA grow tax-free.
Many people see the eventual tax bill on
RRSP withdrawals and think it was a bad
deal. But the RRSP and TFSA give you an
identical after tax outcome if your tax
rate stays constant. It gets even better
because it's common for people to have a
higher tax rate while they're working
and contributing to the RRSP and a lower
tax rate in retirement. In that
scenario, the RRSP offers an advantage
over the TFSA. It is true, as Kyle
points out in the book, that pulling
dollars out of your RRSP at a higher tax
rate effectively results in a penalty
for having used the RRSP rather than the
TFSA. Now, the problem, as Roy explains,
is that we do not know with certainty
what our future tax rate will be. This
does introduce some uncertainty about
the optimal account choice today, but
it's still possible to make sensible
decisions using the RRSP in years where
your income is high relative to what you
expect it to be in the future and using
the TFSA when it's low, or if possible,
just max out both. Next, Roy moves on to
home ownership. He first explains that
it's critically important to consider
the total cost of ownership when buying
a home. Not just the mortgage payment,
but the property taxes and inevitable
ongoing maintenance costs. Not to
mention the potential for the mortgage
payment to increase if interest rates
increase, an issue faced by many
Canadians in recent history. Given the
currently high property prices in
Canada, Roy describes some of the levers
that people can pull to make buying a
house more of a possibility. The first
one is to buy a cheaper home. That may
be obvious, but it's worth saying. It's
not necessary to buy a house that fits
the maximum amount the bank will lend
you, and smaller homes cost less and are
easier to maintain. There are terms to
describe spending so much on a house
that you can't enjoy the rest of your
life, including house poor and
cashration, which are both
self-escriptive as states most people
would want to avoid. The next levers
includes some good rationale for not
stressing too much about having a 20%
down payment, using the FHSA, the first
home savings account, and the RRSP home
buyers plan to increase the amount you
have available due to the income tax
deductions gained from using those
tools. taking out a mortgage with a
30-year amortization rather than the
more common 25-year amortization to
lower the payments on the loan. Finding
a partner before buying a home, living
with your parents to save up for a down
payment, paying off any outstanding
consumer debts to make you look better
to the bank when they assess your
ability to borrow, and earning more
income. I'm not going to go into detail
on all the points here, but each one of
those does have an in-depth discussion
and a thoughtful discussion in the book.
Royy's final point on housing, and where
this channel gets a shout out, is that
renting is not throwing your money away.
a renter who saves the cash flow cost
difference between renting and owning
and invests in the stock market can be
reasonably expected to match the wealth
of a homeowner. The group then shares
some stories about friends who have had
large unexpected housing expenses and
they collectively start to see Royy's
point. Owning a home comes with a
constant flow of unexpected costs. So
constant that they should not in fact be
unexpected at all. The basement leaks,
the air conditioner stops working. A
tree has to be removed. I just had to do
that at my house. The chimneys
crumbling. If renters are diligent about
saving and investing the cost difference
between their rent and the owner's
mortgage, property taxes, and all the
unexpected expected costs of owning,
they can be expected to at least match
the wealth of the owner. I have shown
this in past videos using both
reasonable assumptions for the future
and actual historical data for Canadian
cities. Roy does emphasize a point that
I agree with. Most people who rent will
not save and invest diligently. They
will undersave and invest in shitcoins,
penny stocks, and expensive financial
products. Those are my words, not Royy's
that underperform the market.
Additionally, lots of people, including
some of Royy's students in the book,
have an emotional desire to own. But Roy
suggests here that Canadian society has
conditioned us to believe that home
ownership is a desirable objective and
that it's worth reflecting on whether it
is really a desirable objective for you.
There are additionally lots of
psychological benefits to renting, like
fewer responsibilities, more predictable
costs, and general lifestyle simplicity.
There are valid points on both sides,
but Roy's point is that renting is a
viable option for housing from a
financial perspective. It is not
throwing money away, and it may be the
best path for some people to follow.
Music to my ears. Royy's next lesson on
spending is incredibly important. People
spend money for the wrong reasons,
reasons not aligned with their values
and goals. Roy explains that a lot of
spending is the result of faulty brain
wiring. People often spend money to
impress the people around them, even if
not consciously. And in addition to
that, we are not good at delaying
gratification. The point Roy wants to
hammer home is that most people would
cut back on some of their spending if
they were more aware of where their
money goes. And even small changes in
spending can be a big boost to your
savings rate. Royy's first tip here is a
tedious one to create an exhaustive
multi-month spending summary. The group
agrees that this sounds like a miserable
task, but Roy says that over his many
years of experience teaching people
about personal finance, these spending
summaries have proven vital for many
people to get on top of their personal
finances. Arguably even more importantly
and interestingly, Roy says that he is
100% sure that doing a spending summary
has positively impacted people's
happiness levels. The reason is that it
makes people realize where they are
spending on things that don't bring them
value and it helps them to make sure
they are getting value from the things
they are spending on. As Roy describes
it, you want to maximize the joy units
you're getting for each dollar of
spending. If you can find spending that
is giving you some joy units like
lunches out, but when added up over the
course of a year, those dollars could
have afforded something with a higher
joy unit impact, you might realize it
makes sense to reallocate your spending.
Small numbers make a big difference. For
example, saving only $11 per day for a
year results in over $4,000 of savings.
More if you account for any return, even
a small one earned on those dollars. Roy
brings up a famous quote from Ben
Franklin to drive the point home. Beware
of little expenses. A small leak will
sink a great ship. The next lesson is on
wills, life insurance, and
responsibility. Nobody likes thinking
about dying, but as Roy explains, if you
don't think about it, your estate will
be distributed based on your province's
intestasy laws, the laws that determine
what happens when someone dies without a
will. The problem is that those laws are
often at odds with what you would have
wanted to happen if you had taken the
time to plan for it. It's important to
consider what exactly you want your
estate to achieve and have a will
drafted accordingly. Roy suggests going
to a professional, but acknowledges that
some of the online will platforms can
also work if you have a simple
situation. Personally, I would go to a
professional, especially if you have any
complexity in either your assets or your
estate objectives. Roy emphasizes the
importance of choosing an executive. The
executive is the person responsible for
carrying out the will's instructions,
but it is not a small job and should not
be taken lightly. Royy's last point on
wills is that they should be reviewed at
least once a year. And he also mentions
that when you get your will done, you
also need to draft power of attorney
documents. Powers of attorney give legal
power to someone you have chosen to make
decisions on your behalf in the event
that you become incapacitated. There are
two main types. Power of attorney for
property, which lets someone manage your
money and other assets, and power of
attorney for personal care, which lets
someone make health and lifestyle
decisions on your behalf. It is worth
noting that these have different titles
across the different provinces in
Canada. Similar to an executive,
choosing the right person or people is
important. Finally, Roy moves on to life
insurance. He explains that while life
insurance is extremely valuable in the
right circumstances, it is always a
cost. You want to make sure that you
have an insurance need before you buy
life insurance. Life insurance provides
financial protection for your dependence
in the event of a premature death. An
insurance need means that other people
that you care about would be unable to
maintain their lifestyle in the event of
your untimely death. The most common
example would be your spouse and
children, particularly in cases where
you are the primary income source for
the household. This insurance need tends
to decrease over time as your assets
increase. Roy does walk through how to
quantify your insurance needs in the
book, but I'll let you read that in the
book. The final point that Roy makes on
insurance is one that everyone needs to
hear. Most people will only ever need
renewable and convertible term life
insurance. Term life insurance pays out
the face amount of the policy if the
insured dies. It has a level premium for
a fixed term like 10 or 20 years, and
the insurance expires or renews at a
higher premium at the end of the term.
The alternative is cash value life
insurance, which combines term insurance
and a savings component, where a portion
of the premiums you pay go toward
building up a cash value inside the
policy. That's why it's often referred
to as cash value life insurance. The
savings component means that you're
paying higher premiums overall, often a
lot higher, for the same amount of
coverage. You do also get the savings
component, but Roy explains that buying
term life insurance and investing the
difference is typically going to be a
better option for most people most of
the time. I tend to agree with Roy here.
To finish off in the insurance topic,
Roy discusses disability insurance. For
young people with little financial
assets, their biggest asset is their
ability to earn income in the future.
Life insurance protects that future
income in the event of an untimely
death. But death is not the only way
that your ability to earn income can be
disrupted. In fact, disability is much
more common. When someone becomes
disabled, they may lose the ability to
earn income and even become a liability
to their family. Matt mentions in the
book that he's covered through a group
plan at work, but Roy correctly cautions
that many group plans are insufficient.
One big point to look out for is whether
the policy covers you in the event that
you can't fulfill the duties of your own
occupation or of any occupation. Own
occupation disability coverage is the
gold standard. And you also want partial
disability coverage, cost of living
adjustments, and for the policy to be
guaranteed renewable. Typically, that
means getting additional disability
coverage, even if you do have a group
plan. This is not an area that you want
to skimp on. Okay, I left lots of good
stuff out since this was already a long
video, but I hope the summary was
useful. This is a great book. If someone
asked me for an accessible book to read
as an introduction to personal finance
in Canada, this would be at the top of
the list, even for me. While most of the
facts in the book were not new, the way
that they were communicated gave me a
lot to think about. I'll put a link to
the book in the video description. It's
not an affiliate link. I gain nothing
from you buying it. Thanks for watching.
I'm Ben Felix, chief investment officer
at PWL Capital.